This is Software Engineering Radio, the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net.
SE Radio brings you relevant and
detailed discussions about software
engineering topics at least once a
month. Thanks to our audience and the
partners listed on our website for
supporting the podcast.
Welcome to a new episode of Software
Engineering Radio. This time we have an
episode with Martin Fowler and Rebecca
Parsons about domain-specific languages,
and as usual we start with our guests
introducing themselves, although I don't
think there are many listeners who don't
know you guys, but we should still do
that. So,
why don't you introduce yourself?
Well, I'll start off. My name is Martin
Fowler. I'm a internet loudmouth who
speaks a lot incessantly on the topic of
software development, and my particular
interest in domain-specific languages
was reinforced by the fact that I spent
rather more years than I'd like to think
writing a book about them.
Mhm.
And my name is Rebecca Parsons. I'm the
chief technology officer for
ThoughtWorks. I've got a strong
background in programming languages, and
I've always been something of a
languages geek, and the the work on
domain-specific languages with with
Martin I was primarily focused on it
from the programming languages
perspective, but I also have a
um significant interest in helping
businesses build software better, and we
believe in the long run domain-specific
languages are a good way to go about
doing that. So, we're we're excited
about the opportunity to
um make more people familiar with
domain-specific languages, and hopefully
give us some new use cases for them.
Right.
Um well, okay. So, I guess we should
start by first defining what a DSL,
domain specific language, is since we've
already been talking about it. So, who
wants to go?
Well, I should go with that. And of
course, I should have the definition
right in front of me that I used in the
book.
Hang on a moment.
Okay, so I have here the
the the standard text on the subject.
So nice to be able to say that.
Um
and in it, I have a definition.
So, I define it as a computer
programming language of limited
expressiveness focused on a particular
domain.
Okay. And and I I talk about having
elements to this definition. There are
four of them.
One is that it is a computer programming
language. So, it's not um something like
a business terminology or something of
that kind.
Right. Um I mean, the idea of trying to
build computer systems with a consistent
business terminology using what the
domain driven design people call a
ubiquitous language is a good idea, but
a domain specific language is something
that's executable by a computer.
Right.
The second thing is that it's a
language. So, it has a kind of language
nature, which is a rather fuzzy
definition. But it should have this
quality that feels like some kind of
language, not just for instance a
sequence of API calls or something of
that kind.
Mhm.
The third point I make is that it's of
limited expressiveness.
And that's something, I guess, that I've
particularly focused on
um
in a in a way to distinguish domain
specific languages from general purpose
programming languages.
Um so, to me, the interesting thing
about domain specific languages is that
you you can't write an entire system in
a DSL. You can only use it for sort of
point parts of the system.
Right.
And following from that, the fourth
point is that they tend to be focused on
a specific domain.
And I would also say from a programming
languages perspective that what
constitutes a language, although in our
nomenclature it's very often fuzzy,
there are specific aspects of what it
takes to be a language. And one specific
part of that is what is the syntax of a
language? What does it look like? What
constitutes a legal sentence? And in the
context of a of a domain specific
language, you want that syntax to make
sense to within the within the construct
of the domain. And then the second
aspect of of a programming language
that's useful in this context is the
semantics. What is the behavior or
meaning that is expressed by a
particular legal
legal sentence? And so when we think
about creating a domain specific
language, we have to have an
understanding of what are the concepts
that exist within this domain that we
want to be able to express with this
computer language.
What is the behavior that might manifest
as a result of manipulating these
concepts? As Martin points out, it has
to be an executable language. And then
the third thing is what is a natural way
for people within the domain to put
different constructs together from their
domain into something that would
constitute this executable behavior.
Right. I mean this this topic of limit
limited expressiveness is of course
interesting, right? I mean does this
mean that all DSLs have to be
declarative, whatever that exactly
means? Or I mean some people say that if
a DSL contains things like expressions
or statements, then it's not a DSL
anymore. So can you can you maybe grasp
that a bit more
concretely this limited expressiveness
thing? Because I struggle with it all
the time.
Yeah, well it's one of those vague
boundary condition things.
For me, it's really was triggered out of
this what makes the difference between
a DSL and a general purpose language.
Um being focused on a domain is not
quite enough. Um the example I often
throw in is the R language, which is
used for statistics. Yeah. Um and it's a
very complete language. You can do all
sorts of things with R. Um and although
it's focused on the notion of
statistics,
its power is such that it it has a
different feel to the kinds of things
that
when I was thinking of things like
regular expressions or CSS or something
of that kind.
Um I mean, you could argue that COBOL is
a domain specific language targeted at
certain kinds of business applications.
Just a very big domain.
Yeah, and so that the boundary condition
when focusing on domainness didn't feel
very good. But when you begin to explore
well, it's really about limited
expressiveness, then all sorts of other
things come out of it. Mhm. Uh in
particular, for instance, one of the
arguments against using domain specific
languages is that it's complicated to
build your own parser, for instance.
Yeah. Um but if it's a domain specific
language with limited expressiveness,
the problem is way smaller than it is
than if you're doing a general purpose
language. And that affects a number of
things, I think, in language usage and
design. If you have a simple language, a
lot of the things we assume for general
purpose languages aren't true. Right.
I I I would also say that the question
about expressions depends uh
significantly on what domain that you're
talking about.
Yeah. Um a physicist, for example, is
quite used to working in complex
mathematical equations. And trying to
say a domain specific language that
would be talking about physics wouldn't
have um
expression or equation-like concepts
would would be ridiculous. Yeah. Um
however,
uh, if you look at a marketing
application where you're building
business rules for for determining
offers that might be going to a
customer,
much more than simple addition and
subtraction or maybe percentages, um,
would would not be natural within the
domain. So, we do have to think about it
from the from from that construct. Um, I
do believe part of the reason that, uh,
DSLs have been so hard to work with in
the past though is the fact that when
people start with a limited domain, then
they toss in, "Well, we need
conditionals." Then they toss in, "We
need iteration." And all of a sudden
you've got a general-purpose programming
language that ac- happens to have some
accounting principles, um, in there as
as first-class objects. Um, so, the
ability to
to segregate these domain scripts from
the other processing that goes around
them, I think it is a critical component
for us to be successful, um, in
domain-specific languages. I don't think
that implies it has to be declarative
though. There's still procedural or
behavioral aspects to it. Um, but but we
do want to make sure that that domain
language doesn't get big enough to
become Turing complete. Yeah. Well,
Okay. Um, let's leave it at that. Uh,
Yeah. Yeah, that that that might be a
bit too too extreme, but not not too
far. Actually, I have that I look at
Turing complete I look at Turing
completeness as a smell. Yes. I would
agree.
that there's something probably wrong,
but it certainly isn't an absolute sign
of a problem. Yes.
Yeah, absolutely.
Um, so, you also mentioned before that a
DSL is more than an API or a framework.
Um, and now there are of course internal
and external DSLs where internal DSLs
are embedded in a host language, which
brings them potentially dangerously
close to APIs and frameworks. So, um,
can you try to draw the boundary first
between frameworks and internal DSLs and
then obviously regarding external DSLs.
Well, this is another of these very
fuzzy boundaries, I'm afraid.
The diff- I mean, it's essentially, if
you look at it in its sort of very
simple elements, yes, an internal DSL is
just a string of API calls. Um but
what's interesting is comes down to this
part of our definition of it having a
language nature.
That you should when you're writing an
internal DSL, although you happen to be
writing Ruby, if it's a a Ruby internal
DSL or Lisp, if it's well, less so in
Lisp's case, you shouldn't have a feel
that I'm writing Ruby. It should feel
more that I'm writing this internal DSL.
Yeah. And
I think what it boils down to is
that with API calls, when we when we try
to design an API, we try to make each
API call stand on its own. It's naming,
um it's definition, and ideally, we
should have a limited amount of temporal
linkages between when we make the API
calls. And we typically understand them
by reading down something like JavaDoc,
and it's one method, another method,
another method.
But with an internal DSL, they're
designed to be composed together in
sentences. So, individually, the methods
may not make much sense. You'd look at
them and say, "Well, that's a stupid
name." And some of the ways in which
it's, you know, the way it takes its
arguments and that kind of thing just
doesn't make sense if you look at it
stand-alone. But it makes sense in the
context of a sentence.
And that, albeit a very fuzzy
distinction, is I think the one that
that separates out internal and external
internal DSLs from APIs. It's certainly
the best definition in that sense I've
ever heard because there isn't I mean,
you know, people just say things like,
"Well, it has to feel like a language."
But what what does this mean? And I
think your your your attempt or your
your
you're tying this to the names of the
methods and the independence of the
methods from each other is a very good
very good way to put it.
Yeah, it was that was hinted to me in a
conversation I had with a former
colleague of ours, Mike Roberts. And he
said, "Is the difference between an
internal DSL and an API that an internal
DSL has a grammar?" Mhm. And that was
really what triggered that thought of
thinking, well, of course, you can argue
APIs have grammars, but they're very
limited grammars. With an internal DSL,
you've got a little bit more, and hence
that led me to this thought of
the sentence becomes the fundamental
concept of internal DSL. However,
internal DSLs don't use formal grammars
to specify the valid syntax syntax of a
structure of sentences, right? I mean,
that's one of the main principles that
distinguish them from from external
DSLs, where you usually do use a grammar
or something similar.
Well, I I I would assert as a language
is type that even if you don't write
down the grammar in a formal grammar
specification, you have a grammar for
your language that does exist. And that
that grammatical structure does imply
the relationship between the different
aspects of the sentence. It is obviously
more explicit in in the external DSL
case, but in the internal DSL case,
there is still a grammar because you
have to have some way of mapping between
these these structural elements in your
sentence to the the the semantics that
are supposed to result from the from the
combination of those things, whether
they whether it be nesting, whether it
be modification of a clause, all of the
different semantic syntactic
approaches that we have for building up
a grammar, those are the ways these
different semantic domain concepts can
be related to each other. And that's
something I I
flowed into the book a bit more because
when I'm when I was looking at the
various techniques you have of combining
elements in an internal DSL, I found
there was an interesting correspondence
between which techniques you'd use and
what was your logical grammar that you
might have in place. Certain grammar
constructions implied certain ways of
using language constructs. And I I found
that a very helpful way of thinking
about your options when it comes to an
internal DSL. Right.
So, is it fair to say that all languages
that are friendly to internal DSLs have
some of the same language features like
the ability to avoid parentheses
parentheses parentheses or, you know,
commas or something like that. So, is
there a like this set of language
features that makes the language DSL
friendly?
I suspect so, although it's not
something I uh thought about in a huge
amount of depth. Um but yeah, certainly
the minimizing of unnecessary
punctuation, whether it be keywords or
simple things like commas or
parentheses, certainly helps. Um I think
it also
there are certain constructs that are
useful for instance, the ability to have
closures is really useful because it
allows a a hierarchy nesting that is
otherwise difficult to achieve.
Um well, it's a hierarchy nesting
combined with being able to alter the
execution order.
Um which is useful for that. Um in
addition, I think um significant um
syntactically significant white space
like Python actually becomes a problem
for an internal DSL because if you want
because often you want to format your
DSL differently to the way the language
normally is formatted in order to bring
out the DSL-ish quality of it. And if
you've got
um you if your indentation is
syntactically significant, you can't do
that. And um so, I think that's a a
hampering piece as well. Okay.
So,
one benefit I think of internal DSLs is
that they potentially can interact very
well with the host program. Although,
that of course can also be a
disadvantage if you want to disconnect
the domain people from the
implementation. So,
you want to elaborate a bit on these,
you know, trade-offs, embeddability,
composability with GPLs, and and domain
expert, you know, usability?
Well, that boundary condition I think is
is really quite interesting cuz it
really does cut both ways. I mean, some
problems it's really nice to be able to
mix easily between the DSL and the
general purpose language. And that's
where an internal DSL is very very
suitable. Um the example that
immediately springs to my mind there is
build
description systems such as make, rake,
ant, and the like. Um I've definitely
come to the view that having an internal
DSL, which is what rake, the Ruby build
system, uses is much better than having
an external DSL, which is what make and
ant effectively have.
Mhm.
Um
but there are other problems where it's
good to have a hard line, where you say,
"We don't want to
um if we let that line be too fluid,
then it's too easy for a host language
to overwhelm the DSL or for people to
write expressions that go outside of the
boundaries."
So, it really I think depends on the
problem as to whether you want something
with a hard boundary or a a very fluid
boundary. And um
and and so that's really an interesting
case of sometimes good, sometimes bad.
Yeah.
And and I I would actually turn the the
question around a little bit. Um one of
the
Well, one of the problems with an
internal DSL is that you are bound by
the syntax and the compu- computational
model of your host language. And if you
buy the assertion that what we're trying
to do is express things naturally within
a domain, if what is natural within
within that domain does not map cleanly
to the computational model or the syntax
of of the host language, you're going to
you're you're going to have to alter
what you would like to do in the domain
language to make it possible to to be in
the internal language. So, I would
um I would like to start from what is
the requirement of the language, but
then of course I'm a languages person.
Um
I mean
I I think it's really interesting. I
mean, if we go back two or three years
or four years, and at least stay a
little bit in the mainstream, we had
tools like ANTLR or Xtext, which were
basically uh
tools for building standalone external
DSLs, and there were internal DSLs in
the languages you already mentioned.
Now, things are changing a bit, right? I
mean, for example, with Xtext, while you
can't easily extend Java, you can
include an existing expression language
Xbase. In In MPS, you can easily extend
Java or C. So, and not in a way where
you use metaprogramming with the host
language, but rather by really literally
extending the language definition. So,
that is another form of if you will
embedded DSL. It's not really internal
in the sense as you've defined it, and
it has many of the advantages of both.
You get tool support, you get a real
grammar, uh or whatever the formalism
is, and you still get close integration
between uh you know, GPL and DSL. So, I
think interesting things are happening
there to to give you more options in
this space.
Yeah, I mean, that was it was something
we experimented
um several years ago with intentional.
Uh the idea of just combot composing
different languages within the same
piece of script is particularly nice for
something like where you've got a a
system that's doing doing SQL, and you
can put the SQL right in there. You can
put your code right in there and you can
also have very nice linkage to test
cases right in there as well. Um and I
thought that was a very interesting
direction to take. But this is where you
move into the we're going to need more
sophisticated tools which of course is
what things like Xtext and and MPS are
pushing towards. Yeah. And maybe just as
a teaser uh not too long from the time
when you hear this episode there will
actually most probably be an episode on
SE Radio which explores this idea a
little bit further.
Mhm.
Um okay. So um
and we'll talk about some of the tool
aspects later again. Um
so another concept that I find very
prominent in in your talks and in your
book and which I don't always agree with
in terms of the prominence you give it
uh is that the semantic model.
So so can you elaborate the difference
between you know the semantic model the
meta model of the DSL the abstract
syntax all all these things?
Okay.
Um the example that I like to use to
think about this is if you've got
something that you want to model using
uh a state machine construct.
Um if you have a problem where you've
got to deploy
a hundred different systems and they all
have slightly different behavior but
their behavior can be nicely captured
through a state machine
then a natural route to go certainly if
you're the modeling direction is you say
well let's build a model of state
machines and then I can populate it 50
different ways for 50 different cases.
And that's something database people do
by
having state machine things inside
databases or object people do by
creating object models of state machines
etc. etc.
Now a DSL can be used as part of that
cuz a good way to express a state
machine so that you can write state
machines down is to do it in terms of
writing a DSL.
But what you then got to you've got is
this this concept of a model of state
machines and a DSL that is able to
express things in terms of state
machines.
And my feeling is that they are both
very important. And what's more there's
actually in many ways more important to
this to having a good model.
A lot of the advantages and
disadvantages that people state for DSLs
can actually be stated in terms of
whether they've got this kind of model
or not. They may call it a library, they
may call it a framework, but it's
fundamentally a thing that allows you to
express things in terms of that model.
What the DSL does, I refer to it as a
thin veneer over the model because
it really just allows you to express
what you're doing in the
in that domain a little bit more
cleanly, but it's then going to populate
that model. Mhm. So a DSL has a
syntactic facade around a potentially
complex framework.
Yeah. And the point is if if is I've
seen a lot of DSLs implemented that
don't use this approach. But the problem
that well the advantages of having a
clear model is that for start it allows
you to express semantics in terms purely
of the model without worrying about the
the syntax of your DSL and how you're
going to parse it and all that kind of
thing. It allows you to test the model
independently of how it's populated
through the DSL and that I think is a
very useful separation of of concerns.
Mhm. I think it's also important to
distinguish between an abstract syntax
tree and a semantic model. There may be
a close correspondence, but there may
not be. And if you if you think about
things again from the perspective of the
domain and what the what this DSL is
trying to to relative to the domain, you
have you have concepts in in that domain
and there are there are behaviors that
you want these these concepts to be able
to manifest and that's the semantics of
that domain and you can start from the
domain, what are my sensible I'm trying
to avoid using the word objects, that's
why I'm saying concepts because this
isn't this isn't OO necessarily even,
but so I have concepts within my domain
and I have behavior that might manifest
itself in my domain and there is
something that constitutes in
interaction in my domain that might look
like a procedural
step one, step two, step three or
workflow, but it might look like
something very different like a state
machine behavior
as an example and so I can talk about
the semantics of this language in the in
the language of the domain
and I can talk about the semantic model
in that
in that context and then I simply look
at okay, what is the syntax that I want
to layer on top of this to allow me to
populate the the the representations of
these concepts that I have in my
language and to express the the behavior
that I desire of of these concepts. So
separating out the the the syntax tree,
I think is important
because you the the purpose of the
syntax and the purpose of that semantic
model are in fact quite different.
Mhm.
I mean the the reason why why I why I
sometimes disagree a bit is that first
of all in embedded systems, you can't do
it often because you have to be very
efficient, you can't have a big
framework. So that that's one thing,
right? You you don't want to just
populate a framework, you want to
generate very optimized low-level code.
So that
Well Yeah. Hang on on that point. I mean
in the embedded systems you're talking
about, do you have the parsers for the
domain specific language as part of your
embedded system?
No, no.
Of course not.
Well, well that's the point, right? The
semantic the once you have a semantic
model
and and I didn't talk about this earlier
on, but it it is follow-on thing. You
can then choose to execute that semantic
model directly effectively by
interpreting it or by doing code
generation of the semantic model. Okay,
then we're talking about two different
things and we need to clarify.
Um there is the idea of having a
framework, maybe one that already exists
or maybe one that you've built for the
purpose, for which you then build a DSL,
which basically
populates the framework and then the
framework runs. That does not work in
embedded systems for all the reasons of
the overhead.
Of course, what you can do and maybe
should do is you have uh a cleanly
defined semantic model, which you then
either generate or interpret in embedded
systems, you will probably generate, and
that is something you decouple from the
syntax and the abstract syntax. But
these are two different things.
Well, I guess I see them as the same
thing.
Okay.
how you got there, right? If you've got
an existing library or framework, you
might say, "Okay, I'm going to make that
be my semantic model."
But if you're going from the beginning,
you'll build the semantic model and your
DSL syntax typically hand in hand
together.
Um and then of course it it's it depends
on the circumstance whether you need to
generate or not off the semantic model.
Yes, and and going one step further,
depending on the tool I use,
the language structure will be very
close to what you would ideally define
as a semantic model. And then you can
argue whether you actually need two of
them, right? And that is basically my
point. But okay.
So we've solved that.
But the important thing for me is the
particularly with code generation case,
you don't go directly, you don't write
in your grammar file the generation code
off there, which I have seen people do.
Yeah. Um that's where I feel there's an
opportunity to separate concerns.
Okay, but but I mean, we shouldn't
probably discuss this forever, but if
you use for example Xtext, you you write
a grammar, the grammar automatically
creates a meta model, which is the
abstract syntax of your language, and
then you generate code from that. So,
you don't embed generation stuff in the
grammar, which is as I mean this is this
is Right. That's right?
But, I would not in this case create yet
another, let's say, EMF Ecore file for
the semantic model, and then transform
the abstract syntax created by Xtext
into that one, and then generate code.
Yes. But, but that that depends on the
qualities of your semantic model, and
how closely that maps to what is the
natural syntax within the domain. It
might make sense to go directly from the
syntax tree. It might make sense to go
from the syntax tree to a model that
makes it easier to to do the code
generation. And that's going to be very
problem specific.
Yeah. I mean, for instance, if you're
evaluating arithmetic expressions, then
an abstract syntax tree is an excellent
semantic model. They can you can have
the same artifact playing two different
roles, and that's perfectly okay.
Yeah.
Well, then we agree.
I think so. VIOLENTLY.
IT'S BORING.
OKAY. We already touched the point of
interpretation versus code generation. I
think we should cover that to some
extent. I guess people know it from
interpreters and compilers. It's
basically the same story, right?
Yes.
Yeah. Um it basically when when you're
looking at interpretation,
what you are what what you are executing
against is the semantic model, whether
it be a an abstract syntax tree or or
some other representation. Um and it's
um it it within the the compiler world,
you're very often uh working off of
either an abstract syntax tree or some
other internal representation of the
program, be it a program dependence
graph. So, it it's exactly analogous in
in that context. And the nice thing is
you can make the same kind of choices
that you can make in a language um
uh Scheme, for example, you can both
interpret and compile do to native code.
You have the same kind of choices where
you can have the moral equivalent of the
read about print loop to do quick
debugging and such within the in your
DSL and then when you want to you can
compile it down to to something or code
generate for for more efficient
execution. So there is there is no
conceptual difference between what's
going on here in DSLs and what we talk
about in programming languages and
compilers.
And with perhaps an extra twist that
when you generate code, you actually
have the choice of do I actually
generate effectively a model in data
that I interpret in the generated code
structure or do I just go for straight
ahead
code with no notion of a model in there.
And that has its own trade-offs, but
that's an independent decision of all
the other pieces of the DSL chain. There
is another nice thing that helps to
confuse people and that is that
code generators are actually
interpreters because they interpret the
model and as a side effect they generate
code.
Yes, exactly. Exactly.
The
the output domain for a code generator
is is
is native code and that happens to be
just different than the actual domain of
What I would like ideally is to write an
interpreter and then have some magic of
automatically deriving a compiler for
that.
I think this is known as I'm not really
that's kind of beyond what I really talk
about, but I think it's called called a
partial evaluation. Is that true?
Anyway, the point is have you come
across I mean I know there is work in
compilers in that space, but have you
come across
that kind of approach in DSLs where
where you can automatically derive a
compiler for a target platform from an
interpreter that you've maybe written in
some abstract specification?
DSLs are not nearly that sophisticated
yet. I certainly haven't seen seen
anything that's that's that's equivalent
to to that in in the DSL space. Okay. Um
there are there's certainly ways that
that I could imagine that that you could
do such a thing, but I certainly haven't
haven't heard it haven't heard of it
being done anywhere.
Okay. I mean the first ingredient you
would need there is actually some kind
of formal way of specifying the
semantics, and that is an interesting
question in itself for DSLs, right?
Exactly. And And you know, the way I can
actually see it happening is if you do
have something that is more closely tied
with with a framework where you you
actually have more of more of an ability
to to take advantage of of some
connection between something you have in
your semantic model and executable code
you already have available to you with
this framework. Right. So that's
probably the the the the obvious analogy
that that I can see at the moment, but
um
I don't think that that's I I don't
think that's something that's going to
be uh
I I I don't think that's a that's going
to be a popular early topic. We we still
have a whole lot of questions in terms
of just what constitutes a good DSL,
where the boundaries go, and and trying
to trying to get that far down the road
I think is is still quite a ways off.
Mhm.
Okay. So let's uh come back uh and and
uh address some more uh practical topics
again uh you know, after this theory.
Why would one use DSLs? What are the
benefits?
There are two primary benefits that I
tend to talk about.
Um the first is simple programmer
productivity.
Um for this, my example is regular
expressions. I mean, they're a very
cryptic construct and all the rest of
it, but if you look at a regular
expression
um and you compare it to the code that
you'd have to write without the regular
expression, it's much easier to
understand and modify write the regular
expression. And so, a lot of DSLs just
help in that terms of program
productivity. I mean, that's part of the
reason why Rails got so popular because
they express so many of what they did in
these little DSLs scattered around the
framework. Right.
And people like that.
Now, that is in itself is enough in a
lot of cases, I think. Um but there's
also a bigger prize out there, which is
um for that my example is CSS.
Now, that is a programming language, but
most of the people who program in it
don't think of themselves as
programmers.
They think of themselves as web
designers. And they're describing this
really quite complicated language in
terms of its semantics. Um but they're
able to manipulate it in in terms that
they at least have some sense that they
understand.
Now, the the value here
is
not so much that um with with this kind
of of DSL, you want domain people to be
writing it themselves, although there
are certainly cases where it happens. I
think the biggest gain is if you can get
to a point where domain people can read
the DSL and have a conversation based on
it with developers. Or pair program.
Because then
Hm? Or pair program. Yeah, or pair
program.
Because then what you've got is a very
rich information channel between domain
people and developers. And since that
divide between domain people and
developers is to my mind the biggest
problematic divide we have of many
divisions in software development. Um
anything that can bridge that gap is
really nice. Now, of course, it's not
easy to be able to pull that off.
Um but the benefits can be quite huge in
doing so.
Right. And and just as a remark there,
I kind of distinguish between like
application or business domain DSLs and
technical domain
based on the target audience and many of
the trade-offs we've discussed before
also kind of hinge on this thing. I
mean, for example, external DSLs with
good tool support are better for domain
people, whereas internal DSLs with tight
integration in the programming language
may be more interesting for technical
people. So, there are there are some
relationships there, I think.
Oh, absolutely. I I think I think
internal DSLs are particularly
attractive if your only audience is
programmers cuz then they get to program
in their regular language, particularly
if it's a language that's suitable for
DSLs.
Yeah. But, as you move to more more
external people, then the freedom of
syntax and the freedom of semantics that
you get with an external DSL become a
lot more attractive. Right. Well, and
and even just the expectations of of the
tools. Um I know that that developers
with IDEs, they're they're very bound to
to the keyboard shortcuts and and there
are methods of interacting with a
development environment tool for
developer that seems very unnatural for
for business people.
Mhm. Um when when you watch someone who
is is a true wizard at manipulating an
Excel spreadsheet, they don't interact
with that development environment in the
same way that that a truly expert
developer interacts with with a Java IDE
or with or with Visual Studio. And so,
the expectations that you have around
tools are very different as as well and
and how how it you can uh provide a tool
that that is natural for someone in a
domain is very different as soon as you
get out of out of the technical domain
into the application domains.
You mentioned the E word.
Is Excel a DSL?
No, I think it's a general-purpose
programming language.
Okay.
But, it is absolutely a general-purpose
programming language and a very
interesting platform because of the fact
that it is the most widely used
programming language by people who don't
consider themselves to be programmers.
Yeah. There there is another another a
connection there, I think wherever Excel
is used a DSL is lurking somewhere.
Yes, I would agree.
Yes.
There's actually a
research project going on at the
Technical University in Delft where they
are working on exactly that connection
where they are trying to understand why
and how people use Excel Excel in
business context and and and see to what
extent DSL DSLs can be a better solution
there.
Any other advantages of DSLs before we
look at the downsides no free lunch of
course.
Well, I I do think one of the important
advantages particularly of an external
DSL although you can pull it off in an
internal one it's more difficult is that
you you can express the behaviors
that are associated with those domain
concepts in a way that's natural to to
the domain and this this gets into the
these alternative computational models
where where you can actually think about
a problem and model it and express it as
a data flow system even if you are going
to execute in in a completely different
computational context and so for
not not so much potentially in business
domains but when you start to think
about scientific domains
that ability to to change computational
models I actually think is an important
one and
trying to figure out a way to express
um
express a a concept not only that is not
natural
in the programming languages but even
the behavior is a stretch I mean
programmers are stubborn we know how to
take take an object-oriented language
and make it do whatever we want it to do
but if it's not natural in that language
it's going to be even more difficult for
the domain person to to really
understand what's going on and so trying
to
being able to separate out the semantics
of the model
with this alternative computational
model and then build the execution
engine for that separately. I do think
is is an advantage and it's a place
where you would look to to use DSLs.
That also provides us a way where we can
start to address some of the
some of the performance characteristics
as well where where if you know, if
you're looking at at particular
scientific computations, this this
computational model might be more
efficient than that because we know some
things of the characteristics of the
data. And so those are things if we can
separate those things out, it's easier
to express than trying to explain to
someone, okay, well, you've got to write
two versions of this program because if
your data looks like this, you don't
want to run it the other way.
Yeah.
I mean yeah, go ahead.
Yeah, I think that the alternative
computational models is particularly
interesting to me because I've come
across from time to time teams that will
build
uh
this rich semantic model of part of
their domain in there that's incredibly
productive, but it's
it's both it's a mixed bag because the
people who understand that semantic
model, they can do an enormous amount
really quickly,
but a lot of people find it very
difficult to learn and very difficult to
approach. Yeah. And so one of my hopes
is that people by taking on DSLs or so
oh, by making a DSL as a front end to
this rich semantic model, I can actually
make the whole thing more approachable
because instead of them looking around
in inside data structures trying to find
out where the program is, they can
actually see the program
in a much more explicit form. I mean,
what really is interesting, I mean, when
people start using DSLs, they often do
that because they think, you know, we
can write programs in a more concise way
and we can generate all this crappy code
we don't care about. So that's the first
look at DSLs. Then at some point they
notice, well, hm, actually there is
another benefit. The syntax can be so
that we can integrate domain experts and
and we can capture our business
knowledge. So, that's kind of the next
step. And then even further people come
about this this alternative semantic
models and notice that based on this
they can do much more interesting
things, not just in terms of
writing less code, but making more
interesting analysis, proofs,
correctness, you know, constraint
checking stuff. So, it's really
interesting how as people use DSLs more,
these somewhat more advanced or less
obvious topics become more important.
Yeah. Agreed.
So, downsides, there have to be some.
Yep. Well, I I I thought I always find
the the language cacophony um
complaint an an interesting one because
if you are doing your domain-specific
language properly,
that language expresses the domain. And
unless you believe that you can
effectively program within an
application context and not understand
the language of the domain.
Yes, you've applied a formal syntax to
it and and you've applied a formal
semantics to it rather than the more
informal notion that we often uh carry
around in our head whenever we're
programming in a particular domain. But
those those domains exist and those
language
languages exist. And so, I think all
we're doing in this context is making
those things more explicit and perhaps
because we are being more explicit about
the existence of these different
languages, the the places where these
languages interact or intersect or
perhaps, heaven forbid, conflict, um
will become more obvious because we are
talking explicitly about these languages
rather than them lurking in the
background without us paying attention
to them. So, that that that's one that
that I I I have a difficult time
actually calling it out as a as a
disadvantage. To to me it's it's more a
feature. Mhm.
Yeah, I'm it just occurred to me I might
have to we might have to go slightly
matter cuz we didn't explain what the
language cacophony problem was. So, I'll
explain it shall I?
You may want to put this in front of
I'll leave it up to you.
So, the language cacophony problem is
basically saying well if we have start
using DSLs then this system instead of
just being a Java system, it's got 30
languages in it and people are going to
find it much harder to learn and
understand because I've got to deal with
30 languages instead of one.
Well, otherwise you deal with 30
frameworks. How is that simple?
Exactly.
And that's the counterpoint to that
because you got to learn the frameworks
anyway.
And if the languages are any good then
they make the frameworks easier to deal
with. Now of course a bad language is
going to make things worse but bad stuff
always makes things worse and there are
plenty of bad frameworks out there.
Okay, so let's let's put that into the
undecided category but there must be
some real disadvantages.
Well, there's a real cost to the
building
and you have to build the necessary
constructs to to make a
domain specific language and that input
entails some cost of building and some
cost of maintenance.
Yeah and and I think too when
particularly when you think about
domains that that are changing rapidly
it's one thing to modify your code and
modify your test to express a new
business environment. If you have a lot
of your business logic encapsulated in a
domain specific language and the
business context changes to the point
where
you want a different language, you have
you have a a very different kind of
migration problem on your hands in terms
of how do I map this domain language
to this new domain language. So, I I I
do think there's there's questions
around what does it really mean to
evolve a language um
what does it mean to migrate old scripts
across the evolution within the domain
specific language and and I so I do
think there there's a there's a
complexity there that we really haven't
figured out how to grapple with. And
yeah, and this this is also leads to the
what I find is one of the interesting
comments. It's not just the true of of
domain specific languages, but generally
frameworks as well, which is you have
this tendency to create blinkered
abstractions. Where you once you've got
a good abstraction, it kind of puts your
blinkers on and you can't see things
that don't really cleanly fit into that
abstract
Yeah. Um
and there's a I think a an argument, a
reasonable argument that domain specific
languages can exacerbate that problem.
Um I mean you get it in any case, but if
you've got a really nice DSL and a
really nice abstraction, then yeah, I
can see that there's a definite danger
there that you you're not going to see
things that fit outside of it. Yeah.
I I I think that there's another issue
too in that we really don't yet
understand what constitutes a good DSL.
And so the probability of creating
a language that doesn't necessarily
serve the needs well of the users,
particularly if if the focus is on this
we're going to sit our domain expert
down with our with our developer and
have them pairing on on this. You you if
if you've got a bad language,
you are probably going to make that
communication channel worse rather than
than than better. And we still really
don't know
um how to approach
language design in general for for a
DSL. There there's still a lot of
questions out there on what what
constitutes a good language design. You
know, we we can talk about it very
conceptually, well it should, you know,
naturally express the concept that the
concepts, but what does that what does
that mean? How does that manifest itself
when looking at a particular domain and
a particular language? And so we do have
the possibility of of making the process
worse rather than better if we don't get
the language right.
Mhm.
Yeah.
I I just always think I mean what's the
alternative? I mean not having a
language at all using word documents or
using bad frameworks. I mean you know
bad frameworks which don't capture the
domain are also a problem.
So I guess whenever you're trying to
solve a whole class of problems or a
whole domain then you always have the
problem of what is the right abstraction
and how do you fit in the 20% that don't
fit the abstraction? So so the question
is how quickly can you well so maybe
maybe if you have a domain that evolves
quickly maybe you have to build a
language that allows you to build some
abstractions in the language so you
don't have to change the language if
some abstractions change. Things like
that, right?
Yeah, although if it's really
fundamental changes to the language then
I think there's an issue cuz
the ability to build new abstractions in
the language is to my sign another sign
of a general purpose programming
language.
Well
I
I agree of course but on the other hand
side I mean I have seen examples where
where it does make sense in some limited
cases to to to for example very very
primitive case I have a bunch of
hardware building blocks and the other
question is what properties can I ask
this hardware about like temperature,
speed, whatever. And if you code that
into the language that may be bad
because if the driver now supports an
additional data value you have to change
the language. So rather you put it into
a you know you define these things in
the language you know things like that.
Yeah, but then again I I would say the
word you used though is limited.
Yes. Right, it's limited abilities to
build new abstractions is okay. Yeah.
Yeah. Yeah. Right. Domain specific
abilities in some sense. So Yeah. Um
We already tried to to well so so we of
course prepared this episode, right? So
we have a script a little bit and the
next thing is DSL life cycle and it it
talks about what makes a good DSL and
the idea of layering over a model. We
talked about these things already,
right? So is there anything you want to
add in that space?
Well, I I think what one of the
questions that I often get asked is is
how does this really manifest itself in
the software development life cycle? If
I have a problem, how will I go about
knowing it's time to to have a DSL,
creating the DSL, um if it's an external
DSL, creating the language parser. How
does that then translate into impacts on
my build system? Um how do I deal with
with language evolution? I I think one
of the interesting examples that we that
we have about this in a more limited way
is the use of of um
more more business relevant DSLs for
building automated tests. So, things
like Twist and Cucumber and and some of
those those those testing frameworks
where you you have kind of a middle
ground where where people who are trying
to express acceptance criteria for a
system are are using something like a
DSL uh to to specify their intention of
of of the the test. So, you have, you
know, in a context like that, you might
have
a a a DSL that or a DSL-like thing that
is being used for testing as well as a
DSL that that is being used to to
actually more directly express the
program. So, when when when we look at
the at the life cycle, it is it's it's
the creation and evolution of the
language, it's the creation and
evolution of the language processing
aspects, whether that be the
implementation within the internal
language or the building of the language
processor. Then, we look at particularly
in the case of an external DSL, the
impacts on on the build pipeline.
Um and then we we look at
what do you have to test with with with
a DSL? You obviously want to make sure
that the translation between a
particular sentence in your language and
the semantic model is correct. Um
we can probably, if we're doing external
DSLs,
feel fairly confident that parser
generation tools are going to generate
the right kind of parser, um but are we
actually associating the right uh
semantics to the to the particular
output of of the parsers? Um
so, you want to test the the language
processor itself, but then you also have
to have a mechanism to test the the DSL
script itself. So, I've put together a
program for something, what does it mean
for me as a user to test this? Um and
how might uh how might that testing
phase fit into a standard build
pipeline? So, those are some of the the
aspects of of the the the life cycle
that we have to look at. And then, of
course, as as the language evolves, how
do we migrate scripts
um
that have been written in that DSL so
that they operate in the new version of
the language. Right. Yeah. And then, a
lot of this stuff depends quite a bit on
the tooling, right? Exactly.
can't be discussed in general, I think.
Yeah.
So,
what do you say to people who say, "I
studied computer science 10 years ago. I
never really understood this whole
grammar and parser stuff. It was always
the hardest thing, compiler
construction. And now, you want to make
me build my own languages? Forget it."
Right?
Well, as I always say, there's there's
people there's a common fear of writing
parsers, and there's two reasons why
people have this fear. One is because
they didn't take the compiler class at
university, and they therefore think
that parsers are scary.
I know how you put it.
And the other reason is that they did
take the
parser class at university, and they
know it's It's scary. But the problem,
of course, is that people is that all of
these classes taught parsing in the
context of general-purpose programming
languages. Yeah. And trying to parse a
DSL is a very difficult exercise from
trying to parse a general-purpose
programming language, especially if you
pick something like C, which is a
horrible thing to parse anyway.
Um and that's really the difference. A
little DSL is not at all difficult to to
write a parser for, particularly if you
use a parser tool kit, but even if you
do something some simple technique like
parser combinators, it's not really that
tough as long as the language is is
relatively simple. And again, by
separating out separating out the
semantics into a semantic model, your
exercise is is then just populating that
semantic model. And it again simplifies
the exercise considerably, I think.
And that there there are uh
well-understood, at least in the
language processing community,
well-understood concepts of what
languages are hard and easy to to to
parse. And and we actually have much
better tools. Many people who took a
compiler instruction class actually use
Lex and Yacc. And and you know, um
Antler, as an example, is much easier to
use. Parser combinators are much easier
to to use than Yacc. Although, I do have
a have a a fondness for Yacc, I have to.
I used to teach one of those compiler
courses, after all. Um
But uh
uh
the the important thing is there are
things you can do in the design of your
language syntax to make it easier or
more difficult to parse.
Yeah. And and and the other thing is DSL
programs or DSL scripts tend to be
shorter than large programs. Um it's
probably also a smell if you've got a
million-line pro uh script in a DSL. And
yet, you know, we do have to do things
like compile huge programs uh that have
complex relationships between the
different parts. And and part of of the
the the drive for the DSLs is is to try
to think of things, you know, in a more
limited context. And that is going to
result in smaller scripts with with
potentially fewer interactions between
various parts of the scripts. And so,
all of those things are going to make
the language processing problem easier.
And to take your argument one step
further, if you have relatively small
programs, you can use relatively
bad performing parser formalisms.
Correct. that is why, for example, uh
the guys uh with Alcuin Fisher, they use
SDF, which is a GLR parser, which makes
writing grammars much easier. It's a bit
slower than ANTLR, but who cares? You
with fast machines and small programs.
Exactly. Exactly. Right. And and I guess
another argument you could make is if
you use tools like Xtext and you
actually go through the trouble of
writing a grammar, which may be hard for
people, maybe not, I don't know, but you
just you don't just get a parser, you
also get an IDE. Get more for your work,
so that's even another argument that
people may want to Mhm. Yeah, and I
suspect actually grammars aren't that
scary because people use them all the
time to understand how a language works.
It's relatively common thing. It It's
just all the other stuff and
particularly when you you deal with a
much more complicated language. Yes.
Right.
I mean, it really came home to me when I
was
um preparing some examples for the book
and I
I used the example that I used in the in
the first chapter, which I should
mention is available as a free download,
so I'm not I'm not necessarily
advertising the book here.
And um
it is basically a simple state machine.
And at one point I did it using XML
because that's the of course a common
way of doing a DSL is to wrap it up in
XML and that way you don't have to write
a parser. Yep. So, it took me a morning
to take the XML script and write the
necessary processor to populate the
model from that.
And then the next day I did a custom
language
and used ANTLR and again it took me a
morning, exactly the same amount of
time.
Yeah. Um and I actually used a bit of
ANTLR I'd never used before just to
think just because I felt that would be
easier to talk about in the book. So,
there's a bit of learning curve
involved. Now, okay, I'm a bit more used
to than perhaps the average person is
ANTLR, but not that much. And the point
is it's not really that much harder
um to use those kinds of tools to parse
a simple language.
Yeah.
And then of course
there is one other way to look at it. If
you don't like parsing, then don't use
it. I mean, there are these projectional
editors
uh which don't parse. Um they may have
other challenges, but you don't have to
do this grammar stuff.
So.
Right, and that's internal DSL's
argument as well, of course. You don't
have to parse them. Exactly. Right.
So, um
I guess
we already mentioned this notion of
language workbenches at least. I didn't
I'm not sure we actually mentioned the
word, but we we talked about
think we have yet, really. Yes.
we should. So, why don't you try?
Okay, so I tend We've already talked
about internal and external DSL's, and I
see those as two
main classes of DSL. And then the third
one I see is language workbenches,
which is a fairly broad phrase used for
tools that are specifically there to
allow you to design and build not just a
language in how we normally think about
a programming language, but a whole
environment for interacting with a
language.
Um the examples that triggered this
uh I guess it was back in around 2005 or
so when I first started look at what
Intentional Software was doing.
Uh I first started seeing what MPS were
up to. Um and some Microsoft efforts as
well. But I would say Intentional and
MPS were were my first two introductions
into this space. And they struck me as
"Oh, there's a lot of interesting common
elements here." You you are describing
some kind of metamodel in some kind of
metamodeling environment to lay out your
metamodel.
Um you typically define some kind of
editor that allows you to manipulate
your language in a much more rich way
than just simply typing text. And then
there's typically some kind of tools to
allow you to do code generation out of
that, so that you've got something
that's really executable. You're not
just sort of doing what a case tool
might do and and wander around waving
your hands a lot. You're actually you're
executing something.
And that really struck me
as a very interesting approach because I
mean there are lots of limitations to
thinking of text as a sole input medium.
Now I think there are huge pragmatic
advantages.
Our whole industry is focused around
text. Um but once you get away from that
it was real I mean it was brought home
to me quite nicely one of our
former colleagues, Matt Fammel, was
talking about how we when programming in
a modern IDE like IntelliJ or Eclipse a
lot of the time you're not typing
anymore. You're just hitting alt-enter
to to do it, you know, in giving it
giving the the the the idea hint and
then putting completion codes and the
IDE is then building much more and
you've got a sense of I'm not
manipulating text here. I'm manipulating
a real model of the program. Um and of
course what a tool like a an MPS does is
allows you to really get into that
much more. And I think these are very
interesting tools because not just could
they allow us to do what we currently
think of languages more intriguingly,
but also to go a step forward. So we've
talked about how how I think Excel is
this really quite rich language
environment. If we really want to have
something that's going to communicate
very deeply with domain people, we want
to build languages like Excel.
And that requires these kinds of tools.
Yeah. So I think the potential here is
huge. Um the question of course is how
far we along, how far will it take to be
practical, etc. etc.
Yeah.
One of the one of the other benefits I
see
as a consequence of the language
workbench approach is
the freedom that it gives you in terms
of designing your DSLs. You can be more
focused in the design of your DSL
because this this language workbench
environment
particularly on the intentional side
perhaps not quite as naturally but I
think it's still
still a feature of MPS
where these languages it's easier for
them to cooperate with each other so you
can say I am going to
talk about persistence over here and I'm
going to talk about aerodynamic modeling
over here and I'm going to talk about
metallurgy here and I have a I have the
infrastructure that will allow those
DSLs to cooperate rather than trying to
figure out how am I going to get
something that's going to be natural to
a metallurgist and an
you know the aerodynamic engineer at the
same time
so I I do think that that's something
that that is going to be critical to the
development of domain specific languages
is this ability for those languages to
interact and the workbenches make that
far easier than even the more
traditional
programming language processing
approaches. Right.
I'm in the lucky position of being able
to spend a lot of my time currently
working with MPS and we are we have
actually built an an extension of C that
uses a table notation for decision
tables for example. And so so this stuff
really works and also this whole thing
about language composition language
modularization extension I mean it's
unbelievably cool what you can do. Now I
mean you can also do it with with
text-based tools to some extent right so
would you include Xtext as would you
call that a language workbench? I
generally do yes.
Okay. It's got different styles but it's
still broadly the same thing. So that
was was my impression as well that
you've kind of removed this this
constraint of being projectional to make
something a language workbench.
Yeah I did write that when I wrote the
the articles in 2005 because everything
I'd seen was projectional at that point.
But in fact X X decks was a counter
example of something that came in
without any kind of projectional
capability and and clearly
fit well enough to to fit in.
Yeah.
I mean if you invented, you know,
programming again today, I mean no
sensible person would restrict
themselves to a seven-bit ASCII
characters or Unicode. So,
I think from a conceptual perspective
this projectional stuff is completely
convincing.
And the tools are also really getting
there.
But of course there is this whole thing
about integration with existing worlds.
Yeah. Well, there is also the the change
in the way you think about solving a
problem. Um and we have an entire army
of of software developers out there who
think about solving problems in an OO
fashion or in a functional fashion and
and how you approach a problem is very
different if you are looking at it in
this
uh in this from the perspective
of a DSL. And I think that this is going
to be an interesting transition for us
as we start to experiment with with
different places DSLs can can be used. I
think we're going to be attacking it uh
from a couple of different angles. Um
the technical domains, we already have
lots of DSLs and I think we're going to
see that continuing to advance. Um
there there are many things that that
people are already quite comfortable
with thinking about as a DSL. Rules
languages are are an obvious example.
And and um the concern I actually have
is that people will be so focused on
using a DSL to represent a rules
language uh that they that that they'll
miss the the more general aspects of it.
But but I I do think we're we're going
to see see that that this movement
towards thinking about problems
differently, but there's a there's a
long way to go before the average
computer scientist coming out of
university is is going to think about
solving a problem in this way.
Yeah. It really changes your worldview
if the language is not a constant, an
unchangeable constant anymore.
Yes.
When you talked about these um
alternative computational models, I
mean, imagine you could reuse a state
machine language and then embed a
domain-specific action language into it.
Right? Things like that actually become
possible. So, that's it's really cool.
Yeah.
Yeah, and it's one of the things that
and and is
the problem with doing anything like the
the book writing idea is you always have
to kind of put limits about what you do.
Um one of the sad limits was really
deciding I couldn't really delve into
the language workbench area. I haven't
really looked that much more in it over
the last year or so, but it is something
I'm I need to look more at again because
I think it's it's got such potential.
Well, let's put it this way. Initially,
when I read your book and noticed that
you didn't talk much about domain of
language workbenches, I was a bit
frustrated, but then I thought actually
this great because now I can write the
book on these tools.
Exactly.
So, everything has two sides, I guess.
Yeah, exactly. And and I I do think
there's a lot of huge amount of
potential in that area. It's It's kind
of odd in a way. People are very excited
at the moment about new languages and
functional languages, the Scalas, the
Clojures, the F Sharps and all the rest
of it. And I must admit part of me feels
kind of well, no. I mean, the really
interesting stuff is what you can do
with a language workbench.
The amount of attention moved into that
space, then I and I think that's where
the real you're going to get a really
big shift.
Yes. I mean, the the the other languages
they can make small gains, but the
really big gain would come through the
language workbench direction.
Yeah.
So, um we are at the end of our prepared
notes. Um did we forget anything? Is
there anything you want to add that I
kind of skipped or that kind of didn't
get the necessary attention?
Nothing leaps to mind. No, I
I got in the points I wanted to make.
Okay, if we were on television, you
should now, uh, you know, put your book
into the camera so people can see it.
So, we have to
we have to do that verbally. Um, yeah,
we're on Skype here. So, I mean, the
book is called, uh, Domain-Specific
Languages and the author is obviously
Martin Fowler and and Rebecca. So, so
people should be able to find it.
Yeah, easy enough to hunt down.
Yeah.
Okay.
Good. Then, um,
I thank you very much for being on the
show. It has, um, we've been planning
this for a while and I'm really glad
that it worked. Yep. And
Same here. Thank you. I guess then
that's it. Thanks for being on the show
and, uh, well, talk to you sometime soon
on some conference.
Yeah, hope so.
Thank you, Markus. Bye.
Thanks for listening to Software
Engineering Radio. SE Radio is an
educational program brought to you by
Hoster Europe. If you want more
information about the podcast and the
other episodes, visit our website at
se-radio.net.
If you want to support us, you can
donate to the SE Radio team via the
website or you can advertise for SE
Radio, for example, by clicking on the
Digg, Reddit, Delicious, and Slashdot
buttons or by talking about us on
Twitter and Facebook. You can also
support us by joining the team and
shouldering some of the work.
To contact the team, please send an
email to team@se-radio.net.
Or, if your feedback is specific to an
episode, please use the comments
facility on the website so other people
can react to your comments. This episode
of SE Radio, as well as all other
episodes, are licensed under a Creative
Commons 2.5 license. Please see the
website for details.